what I want to talk about today is what
emergence is as a phenomena as a
property that's actually essential to
understand the nature of the universe we
live in
and it's actually essential to
understand what it means to be human and
that is essential for understanding the
basis for meaning for ethics for
existentialism and then also what that
portends
for the future of civilization and
addressing some of the things that are
concerning and that are exciting okay so
you can consider the next 20 minutes or
however long this is as kind of an
extemporaneous rambling ode to emergence
itself right a kind of love talk about
how cool it is that universe actually
has this property and that we can
understand and participate within so
let's start by defining what is
emergence emergence means something new
arises that wasn't here before
all right we all kind of have that sense
intuitively but scientifically how the
does that happen how do you bring
particles or planets or anything
together and all of a sudden the hole
has some properties that none of the
parts had like where do they come from
which is why in in the fields of science
that steady emergence which evolutionary
theory and biology and system science
and complexity theory study it it's
considered the closest thing to magic
that's actually a scientifically kind of
admissible term but it's still sketchy
right in terms of the really
understanding how this thing works and
because how do we get fundamentally new
things out of relationships of things
where that didn't exist before this is
this fascinating how do you have a cell
that respirate s-- made up of molecules
none of whom respirate and so it's just
really interesting when you actually
think about this right we we have a coin
a paired term does anyone know what the
term is that is key and understanding
synergy in emergence is synergy synergy
and emergence are two sides of the same
phenomena synergy means whole that's
greater than the sum of its parts
emergence is what is that greater it is
what is the new stuff that emerges out
of bringing things together
and so synergies more formally defined
as properties of whole systems that
aren't found in any of the parts taken
separately which also means that are
fundamentally unpredicted by the parts
taken separately which portends a future
that is fundamentally ontologically
unpredictable from the current state of
the future which is very different than
a mechanistic clock unfolding Newtonian
understanding of the future and yet
still actually makes sense in terms of
scientific laws super interesting right
so synergy is this property of
relationship where the whole has new
properties that the parts didn't have so
emergence is a result of synergy synergy
as a result of relationship that makes
sense and relationship is a result of
attractive forces there are some kinds
of attractive forces whether it's
gravity bringing dust together into
planets or planets the other into solar
systems whether it's electromagnetism
bringing subatomic particles together
into atoms or the strong force bringing
quarks together into protons each of
those are emergent properties driven by
synergy driven by relationship driven by
attraction or whether it's bringing
these people together via pheromones or
love or intellectual affinity or a topic
that we're all interested in like
creating a better world
there's some attractive forces and so
Bucky fuller called love metaphysical
gravity in the same way that gravity and
physical forces act on physical bodies
to attract them we have medical physical
forces that act on metaphysical bodies
to drive attraction but think about so
imagine if you think about all of the
attractive forces as expressions of a
fundamental principle of universe of
allurement that there is a principle by
which separate things have reason to
come together that offers advantage that
being separate doesn't have and you
think about all of the forces as special
case applications of that imagine if
that wasn't the case imagine if we had a
universe where allurement wasn't a
fundamental principle of it and the
whole thing would have stopped at
quantum foam right you have quantum foam
emerge you don't even quite get to the
point of subatomic particle and that's
it because nothing attracts two then
halves energy and emergent properties I
have a friend and collaborator Marc
Gaffney who calls this universal
story why at the heart of the
evolutionary story is this love story
which is that it's actually a traction
driving the whole evolutionary
story right attraction driving
relationship driving synergy driving new
emergent properties driving net novelty
and new creation and the arrow of
evolution so we can actually understand
the arrow of evolution itself in terms
of this set of phenomena together does
that make sense so then evolution in
complexity theory is defined most
generally in terms of more elegantly
ordered complexity that's actually the
best definition we have in terms of
mathematical complexity theory coming
out of Santa Fe Institute the definition
has the word elegance built right in it
because it's again one of these actually
fairly mysterious properties but it's
key to it which is bringing things
together doesn't give you emergent
properties bringing them together in a
particularly elegantly ordered way does
so think about think about all the parts
that make up a cell right you've got all
these nonliving parts DNA and cell
nucleus structures and all the different
organelles and cytoplasm and they're all
not living and then the cell is living
but if you brought all those parts
together but you didn't arrange them as
a cell it was just a bunch of molecules
it wouldn't be that interesting right
just be Goo if you took the 50 trillion
cells that made you and you didn't
arrange them exactly this way and you
just had like 150 pounds worth of cells
it would be much less interesting even
though there'd be just as much
complexity you wouldn't have an order in
the complexity where the emergent
property comes that's actually the
relationship it's not just heaps coming
together it's not just complexity it's
wholes and the difference between a hole
and a heap is order and a specific set
of patterns of order this means not
every relationship is synergistic some
relationships are entropic they actually
create the opposite direction of new
emergent properties they destroy some
properties that were already there right
almost everyone has some examples
but you bring chemicals together that
rather than self-organizing to create
higher ordered molecules with new
thermodynamic properties they have an
exothermic entropic reaction and they
drop to lower levels of organization
right this is true at all levels so it's
not just relationship it's specific
kinds of relationship that maximize
synergy this is a key thing to
understand about the nature of universe
it's also the case that if you bring the
same thing together a bunch of the same
thing you don't get very interesting
synergies you get very interesting
synergies when you bring different
things with different properties
together in the right format where then
you have the properties of each of those
things and then the properties of the
relationship between those which is the
new stuff and you get emergent so you've
got hydrogen and you've got oxygen which
are different things and you bring them
together and you get water in the basis
for life but neither hydrogen or oxygen
at room temperature or liquids right and
so this is a fascinating thing so we're
actually very interested in having deep
synergistic relationships with
differences that lead to fundamentally
new emerging properties so it's not just
net complexity it's ordered complexity
and it's elegantly ordered complexity
and then when you get a new property
then universe selects for that right
that new property offers some
evolutionary advantage to that system
that a system that didn't have that
wouldn't have so things can come
together all kinds of ways but the ones
that come together most synergistically
offer and confer the most advantage in
Universal exports so universe is
actually selecting for more differences
right so it's selecting for diversity
and then more synergistic combinations
across those differences that and it's
both of those more diversity and more
unification across the diversity right
more agency and more symbiosis at the
same time is what defines the arrow of
evolution does that make sense
things that are separate autonomous
agents right so like a cell you can
think of as having its own agency right
its own ability to act and its own
boundary and periphery but you bring a
bunch of cells together and this
collection of cells can reflect on
consciousness and existentialism and
have a conversation like this even
though none of those cells on their own
do that right and it's different kinds
of cells you couldn't do that with just
neurons it takes neurons and glial cells
and immune cells and stem cells etc to
all come together so more agency more
differentiation more orderly
relationship more synergy all of that
comes together and the net defining
thing is emergence how much fundamental
new advantage arises and that's what
evolution selects for and so if it
wasn't for this whole combination of
things together is this the message that
says five minutes left fascinating so so
I I'll see if we can go very quickly
through that was the first 1% of what I
hoped to discuss so I'm going to just
skim over the top of a bunch of topics
and hopefully paint a distorted least of
an arc that's interesting so the
evolutionary universe story the kind of
noobest story of universe we have
emerging from the intersection of all
the sciences is that we have an
evolutionary universe that doesn't
require a creator agent deistic or
theistic god to create but is also not
just random highly improbable set of
movements to get us here but there is a
set of properties that give us a
self-organizing rather than creative
agent creative principle universe that
is moving towards more elegant ordered
complexity and with that story on the
physical you also have the evolution of
consciousness structures themselves
right as you move from a reptilian
nervous system to the increased orderly
complexity of the mammalian and then a
neocortical and then prefrontal nervous
system you move from the kinds of
sentient that map to that of pain
pleasure at reptilian to emotional to
cognition to abstraction so we have a
universe that's moving in the direction
of not only more elegance but greater
depths and
of consciousness itself now this defines
an arrow of evolution that reifies
meaning in a very interesting way and
one of the things that's so interesting
is with our capacity for abstraction we
cannot just think about our experiential
self of the moment but we can think
about ourselves in abstract terms we can
think about time abstractly deep past
and deep future right and that is what
allows us to actually understand
evolution itself it's an understanding
of deep past and fossil record and
astrophysics they give us a sense of the
ability to abstract laws that of how
that change occurs over time that allows
us a deeper insight as to how we got
here and then also the ability to vision
a future fundamentally more beautiful
and more interesting and then be part of
that creative process so it's it's
worthwhile just noting that our
prefrontal cortex and our capacity for
abstraction is a pretty new phenomena
evolutionarily right and it's also very
powerful set of capabilities and when
you have a new phenomena that's very
powerful you're not going to know how to
use it that well many of its
applications will be destructive until
you figure it out so we can think about
the future as worried we can think about
the past as regret we can think about
self abstractly in terms of negative
self comparison so then we have
spiritual ideals emerge they basically
say this is all bad right mind and the
ability for abstraction like this is bad
we should not think about the future at
all or think about the past and just be
in the moment like the other animals and
children are see how happy they are but
it's an it's a regressive spirituality
that is actually rejecting the
fundamentally novel human capability
that emerged rather than say let's learn
how to use it well for its evolutionary
purposes in a fundamentally evolving
universe so if we learn how to use it
well then we say how can we learn from
the past how universe works to be able
to imagine a future in an omni
considerate way that is has
fundamentally less suffering and higher
quality of life across all meaningful
quality of life metrics for all life
right that is Omni considerately true
good and beautiful then how can we apply
all that learning now to actually help
create that world and in doing so we
stop just being a part of the whole but
in our ability to think about the whole
and think about the direction of the
whole
can actually become an agent for the
whole this huge right the bee is
serving this huge role in evolution by
pollinating the plants that make the
atmosphere that make us but they don't
know they're doing that and they can't
consciously figure out how to do it
better but we actually have the
capability of looking at what the whole
story is and identifying as well the
whole evolutionary impulse of universe
brought me about and then woke up to
itself in me and so in a meaningful way
I am actually the evolutionary impulsive
universal woke to itself in a form that
has adequate ordered complexity to
contemplate that and then get to
consciously choose how to participate
with it to be in a not just not just a
aboard Spaceship Earth but crew right to
help steer the direction of evolution
and cosmos and so we move from evolution
as a mostly unconscious algorithmic
process that selects for dominance now
to a process that can be mediated by
conscious agents they can actually
forecast a more beautiful future and
select to help create that does that
make sense so when we don't identify as
evolutionary's then we can be actually
kind of we identify as nouns rather than
verbs and we stay stuck where we're at
and then we need pain as an evolutionary
driver and then emergence through
emergency is how we grow as soon as we
identify with the inexorable 'ti of
evolution and ourselves as evolution
incarnate we stopped needing pain to
push us because our whole
purpose for being for becoming being
becoming are actually matched there are
two sides of the same thing is the lure
of the becoming is the bringing about
more of the timeless properties of the
infinite in time right more of the
infinite through the finite this
actually becomes the basis of our
existence that everybody knows that when
you are in the experience of creating
beauty that didn't exist before in
universe that adds to universe it's
uniquely yours to create you feel a kind
of aliveness it's not matched by
anything else
in lieu of not doing that the emptiness
causes all kinds of addiction right
because that's fundamental to what we're
actually here to do now when we all
identify as evolutionary's we obsolete
the
ETA's paying for a driver does that make
sense
because we have a pull driver rather
than just needing the push driver when
we also identify as fundamentally
interconnected parts of a interconnected
universe rather than separate things we
stop thinking that there is any
definition of success for self that
isn't the definition of success for the
whole and we stop thinking that the idea
of advantaging ourself at the expense of
something else we're inexorably
interconnected to make sense at all
so we are all agents for an
interconnected whole where our sense of
self is our self is actually an emergent
property of the intersection of this
system with the rest of universe it's
actually key in terms of emergence
yourself as an emergent property of the
whole universe because even though you
wouldn't exist
in the same way without your brain and
your body you also wouldn't exist
without the atmosphere and the trees
that make it and the plants and bacteria
that make it and the gravity and
electromagnetism and foundational forces
like the concept of I separate from
universe is a misnomer does that make
sense so the concept of a life path for
ourself it isn't a life path for
universe as a misnomer or advantage for
self so when so then we get in the
deepest sense when Einstein said the
idea that there are separate things is
an optical delusion of consciousness and
in reality there is one reality that we
call universe of which we are all
inextricably interconnected facets and
your experience of self is a facet of
that now what's so fascinating is
that it is interconnected with all of it
it's an expression of the foundation of
all of it and it's also completely
unique in all of universe it's a unique
facet non fungible unique right what
that means is you have something to
offer universe in your experience and
your creativity that no one else has to
offer exactly that way which means if
you don't offer it like if Salvador Dali
hadn't done Dali Michelangelo didn't do
Dali I sure wouldn't have done Dali Dali
just wouldn't have happened
and so universe would have been
fundamentally less
so when you get that your own
self-actualization is compulsory right
you have an obligation to it but then
when you get that everyone else if they
don't self actualize universe is less
your participation with helping everyone
else self actualize is also compulsory
so competition is an obsolete concept
symbiotic to remember universe moves
towards more differentiation more
novelty and then more symbiosis across
that novelty for more emergence and what
we're moving towards is a civilization
where everyone actually identifies this
way as a emergent property of the whole
as an interconnected part of universe
with a unique role to play with unique
synergies with all the other unique
roles to play and then with that synergy
with that human participation then
humanity actually becomes a thing it
actually becomes an emergent property
right now it's an idea but we don't have
humanity we don't have civilization we
have humans bumping right it's we have a
bunch of organelles that haven't
organized as a cell that starts
breathing right you don't have behavior
of the whole that is centrally
unconsciously self-organizing but we can
and I would actually say and and this is
what I wanted to have more time to get
into but to just foreshadow quickly if
we cherry pick from the huge data sets
about where Humanity is going right now
we can see that things are exponentially
changing which means changing it more
and more rapid and more and more
significant rates and you can
cherry-pick metrics where things are
getting exponentially better and that's
true and other things we're getting
exponentially worse and that's also true
which means the future that you predict
if you just follow any of those curves
is not happening if things are getting
exponentially better and worse at the
same time does everybody kind of get
that that's happening on different
metrics then that doesn't mean things
are getting better or worse it means the
current system is destabilizing
and that means self terminating and then
we either have a discrete phase shift to
a lower order entropic system or the
emergence of a higher order system that
is foundationally different than the
current system we have in every in every
way so the things getting bad
are the pieces that can be reorganized
to create a new civilization with a
foundationally new structure right
biosphere metrics are getting
exponentially worse from misapplication
of technology technologies right
application are making things
fundamentally better but technology is
giving us the capacity to do things like
have data analytic capabilities to
inventory all the world's resources to
then be able to allocate all the world's
resources to meet all the world's needs
with optimum efficiency we never have
that ability before like the
transportation and communication
technologies it can actually make us a
global civilization we never had that
before right
and so the technological capacities that
require us to step up otherwise we you
know self extinctions very real thing
also make possible a discrete phase
shift and evolution that's characterized
by three major things and this will be
where I end at the level of social
systems primarily economics the key
shift we're going to move to is a moving
from a differential advantage economy
it's defined by private ownership
valuation based on scarcity and
differential advantage to an economic
system that is defined by making sure
that the incentive of every agent and
the well-being of every other agent and
the Commons is perfectly aligned with no
externality meaning we actually
understand that it's an interconnected
system we identify all the externalities
and internalize them so the system is
actually defined by systemic advantage
for the whole this is not communism or
socialism or capitalism it's something
that was not possible before to even
anticipate but it is how your body works
where none of the cells are advantaging
themselves at the expense of the other
they're doing what's best for them
what's best for the whole symbiotically
at the same time right and so that's the
key net shift at the level of
macroeconomics and correspondingly
governance and all of our social
structures at the level of
infrastructure in the built world we're
moving from a linear materials economy
where we extract from the earth at
ever-growing rates unsustainably from
finite resources and then turn it into
trash to a closed-loop materials economy
where the trash is the new stuff we stop
extracting from the earth stop producing
waste and we actually have a post growth
negative entropy closed-loop materials
economy where we can live ongoingly a
progressive
higher and higher quality of life
sustainably with the biosphere so that's
the infrastructure shift that's the
social structure shift and the
superstructure the mimetic shift is this
awareness of all of us as facets of one
integrated self evolving reality where
the well-being of everyone the
well-being of everyone else the
well-being of the Commons are not
meaningfully calculable separate from
each other now what's so interesting is
there used to be such a thing as local
problems when Gandhi was working with
home rule for India it was largely and
thought of as an Indian problem and it
didn't directly affect everybody right
when people in the u.s. wanted to or who
founded the US wanted to leave British
Empire there was somewhere else to go
and it was a you know a local problem
right now when we deal with species
extinction and ocean acidification and
peak nitrogen peak phosphorus they're
all global issues and you can't solve
them without China and without India and
without the u.s. without everyone
participating so the idea that we have
local issues is gone our level of global
infrastructure and technology is made to
where we have all global issues and they
are actually existential they are
threatening of the biosphere no no one
has ever had issues in the history of
humanity that threatened the ability of
the species to continue nor did they
have ones that they had to face
eminently in short-term nor do they have
the capacity to actually face those
kinds of things the data science the
technology that could build something
fundamentally new what that means is we
have the most significant work that
humanity has ever had with the most
significant capabilities which also
means the most potential to impact the
biggest picture that any humans have
ever had and it's easy to think about
that and then get caught back into like
you got to do next as part of to
win at the current system that is going
extinct but winning at a system that is
obsoleting the capability of life on
Earth to continue winning at a dying
system is not an interesting win right
if you ever think about the definition
of heaven where you're in heaven and
there are people in hell and you're
happy you have to be a psychopath
you have to be able to separate from the
experience of other sentient things
enough that you can be totally stoked
with that level of suffering
well the idea in this world that the
level of intensity of suffering that's
happening can be happening and you can
just be stoked because you're killing it
in your life you have to be mildly
psychopathic if we want to not be
Psychopaths then there is no definition
for success for ourselves it is not
definition of success for everything and
now when we start really taking that
seriously everything changes and
then you start saying well what can I
actually do to make my life of greatest
use to all life and then your answer to
that question if you take it seriously
and really study and really work on it
and don't just like ask the question get
overwhelmed give up and go back to
current stuff you're at you're
progressively better answer to that
question will lead to the emergence of
your life meaning and Dharma and path
and correspondingly the emergence of
civilization making it that's it